[Music]
in this session we're going to talk
about the exciting additions to the
analysis mode on list pages in business
Central both when it comes to adding
columns for fields and related tables
opening Excel uh and creating direct
links to analysis mode uh views from Al
code but first let's recap a little
bit back in 2023 release Wave 2 we
launched the ability to analyze data on
list pages with this you could quickly
extract insights from your data directly
inside a business Central with no need
to involve Developers for instance you
could pick columns reorder them set up
additional data filters group and pivot
and save your analysis for repetitive
use this has been a great success uh
including the later added co-pilot
analysis assist that allowed you to
create these views using natural
language
but a challenge has been analyzing more
complex cross entity data relationships
which still has required developers
creating
queries we're super excited that we have
now empowered users uh even more
addressing exactly this Blan can you
tell us more so that's why in this
release we're introducing a new feature
that will allow users to add fields from
reality tables and Pages Direct direct
ly in analysis mode this will allow
users to make their own data sets from
including different data sources and
also perform complex analysis on this
and all of this directly from the web
client again as Peter mentioned without
having to code
anything um and this is coming this
release but it's also coming in a minor
so you will have to wait a bit more so
it's estimated at 26.2 or
earlier so that was the feature but now
let's H jump straight into the demo to
see how it actually works okay so now
I'm going to open my say line page and
it's already in analysis mode so you are
probably already familiar with this View
and now I can explore a bit this data
set and I see it's missing some
information especially around the
location so I want to add that
information into this list so now I can
actually do that and I'm going to try to
get some information from this sales
order list because I know we have some
about the the
location so if I open the menu from the
analysis stab then I can see this new
action over here which is add columns
from and when I hover over it I will see
a suggestion of all the tables where I
can add data from and these tables are
the ones that already have a table
relationship in a to the right I can see
what kind of relation is that so for
example in the customer this will join
the data where the sell to customer
number in the sales lines matches the
number on the customer
table and when we do so we also perform
a left outer joint but that's it for the
technical details let's go ahead and
find our sales head
table can also click on that and then
that will open a new window where I can
see the source table that I have
selected I can also see the list of H
table fields that I can add to my to my
data set
but we also know that users are usually
more familiar with Pages because this is
actually what surfaces to the H in the
client and that's what users use in
their everyday life so that's why we
have also added the option to just view
all the list pages and card pages that
Implement that table and then I can just
look for in this case I wanted the sales
order list so I'm going to click on that
and then I can see the pages from the
sales order list which are the ones that
I'm familiar with so now I can just look
up for the
fields that I want to
add so um let's add some of the
information
regarding the location of this
invoices and I just click okay we'll get
a a short disclaimer when I add fields
for the first time just to make the user
aware that um calculated fields are
going to be removed and there's also
some limitations with opening Excel
regarding the number of rows that we can
actually show but I'm just going to go
ahead and click okay and then if I
scroll all the way down to my to the end
of my list I see I already have that
data in my list so that's pretty nice
and then of course I can also move my
columns around and rearrange them how I
want or I can also click on a column
menu and add them from there and then
they will be added next to it so let's
for example add more information
from the customer because I don't really
have that much
here so let's pick up the customer
list and I'm just going to pick up the
name perhaps the
Conta and there we go they have been
inserted next to the customer number so
I already have more information
there and of course I can do all the
operations that I would usually do with
a regular IG grid so for example I can
just go ahead and hide or um show any
column I can also Group by this columns
so for example let's group my data by
the region and let's also add some
grouping by the customer name so now I
can see my invoice is very nicely
grouped then I can also of course pivot
if I want to see the aggregation columns
or I can also set some filters so for
example let's look just as at the ones
in the US and that's it so of course the
data set can grow quite big with all
this added columns so if I'm done with a
particular H column or a table I can
just go ahead and remove the column or
for example remove all the columns from
this table so in this case customer
table while I also keep my their columns
over
here um and yeah once I'm done with it I
can also of course share it as I would
usually do with copy link and then also
my colleagues can also have access to
this data set so as you saw that was
super easy I could very easily from the
client just add fields from other tables
without having to do any Al code so just
as a short recap of what we have seen
you can now add fields from related
tables and you can do so using the add
columns um option in the
menu and these uh tables that uh you can
out from are actually those that have
already a table relation in a so that
those are the ones that will show up and
we also filter out those that H where
the user doesn't have access because for
example they are obsoleted they are
temporary or just because they are
guarded by some
permissions um then when we We join
tables we also perform a left outer
joint this means that it also matters
the order in which you perform these
joints um and it's also possible to join
the same table through different table
relationships um and you would also have
the same uh capabilities as you do with
the regular columns so you can also hide
them you can show them you can reorder
them as you would like you can also
freeze them left or right you can set
filters you can group you can pivot on
them and you can also H this will be
also exported to
excel the only limitations that we have
with this redit H fields are that
copilot assist is not just supported on
them so we won't be able to recognize
them and also that calculated fields are
not supported therefore they will be
ignored when performing the
analysis thank you Blan it's it's super
awesome to see the ability to add fields
from related tables or Pages however you
want to see it in the analysis mode tabs
uh basically you know creating Advanced
uh views on data and and essentially
building queries on the Fly and
empowering the end users to do this
without having to involve a developer
for for super super nice insights
capabilities but we have more
Improvement
for the analysis mode uh first out is
the ability to open the data in an
analysis mode tab in Excel actually Blan
alluded a little bit to that before when
she talked about the capabilities and
this allows um you as a user to do
further analysis using all the
well-known powerful Tools in Excel and
you can do this uh from the uh context
menu on the data area uh which works in
all versions or you can do it from the
an is tab context menu which is
supported from 2024 release Wave 2 as a
basically a back port in version
25.3 so Blanca can you show us how this
works all right yes so let's go back to
the analysis view that I have just
created with relateded columns and then
if I go to the menu of my tab then I can
find this new action opening Excel then
I can click on it and I will have my new
Excel shet generated
and then I just open it and I can see I
have all the data that I could see the
client and also including my related
columns over here so now I can just use
this and just share it or use it in some
other
scenarios and that's it yeah thanks
black very very nice I mean not only the
power within the client to add related
tables but actually also pull them out
as part of opening in Excel for further
anal Anis should really really Empower
users for data analysis in this release
so the last addition uh to the analysis
mode is really a feature for developers
uh which allows creating URLs that opens
a page in analysis mode and this is uh
something that builds on the URL support
for layout U parameter that we added in
uh 2024 release Wave 2 um and in this
release we're now adding that the AL get
URL method um has a parameter that you
can specify that you want for instance
the analysis layout uh when creating the
URL so let's see a quick example uh here
we see that when I call the get URL I
put in analysis as part of the uh
parameter in the call and the resulting
URL that gets gener repetive platform
you can see at the end how the analysis
layout is appended to make sure that
this page link that opens in analysis
mode so if uh you're new to analysis
mode and you thought what we brought in
this release was super exciting but you
want to know more about the feature uh
including the analysis assist uh
co-pilot that Blan mentioned and that as
she said is not supporting adding
related fields yet then I suggest that
you watch these previous launch event uh
sessions there will be links to them in
the description for this uh video as
well
so thanks for joining uh this session uh
staying to the end uh I hope you enjoyed
the improvements we have made in the
analysis mode uh in this release that
really unlocks the power uh for cross
entity data analysis for end users
without having to have a dependency on
developers actually going in and
creating this support that both
increases agility and lowers the cost do
note that this feature is planned to be
available after General availability of
the release so right now we are looking
at likely the minor update
too thank you and enjoy the other launch
sessions